University of Arizona Folklore Committee records, 1943-1979
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections
University of Arizona Folklore Committee records, 1943-1979
SWF 002
University of Arizona. Folklore Committee.
13 linear feet
This collection contains, collector files, subject files, administrative files, including Committee correspondence and annual reports for the University of Arizona Folklore Committee records.
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections PO Box 210055 Tucson, AZ 85721-0055 Phone: 520-621-6423 Fax: 520-621-9733 URL: http://speccoll.library.arizona.edu/
Restrictions
None.
Historical Note
The University of Arizona Folklore Committee, founded in 1943 by Professor Frances Gillmor, created the Folklore Archive in 1945 to conserve folkloric materials being collected statewide by the interdepartmental Committtee. The committee collected songs, tales, remedies, and interviews from all over Arizona, with some extensions into Sonora, Mexico. Dr. Gillmor chaired the committee until her retirement, when Dr. Byrd H. Granger asumed the chair. Upon Granger's retirement in 1978, the Folklore Committee was dissolved. In 1979 the University of Arizona Southwest Folklore Center was created to continue its functions, and it assumed the Folklore Archive into its materials.
The focus of the material collected by the Folklore Committee was narrative and folk music traditions of English and Spanish-speaking peoples of the Southwest. The committee collected only a small amount of material concerning Native American folklore.
Organization
This collection is organized into six series:
I. General Administrative Records, 1943-1977
II. Subject Files, 1945-1979
III. Collector Files, 1945-1979
IV. County Files, 1945-1979
V. Informant Files, 1945-1979
VI. Master Files, 1945-1979
Scope and Content Note
Mexican-U.S. border folklore is strongly represented in the collection, which includes corridos and other songs, and tales and interviews concerning old customs. Mormon folklore also forms a significant portion of the collection, particularily songs. Much of the material is the product of collections by schools, clubs, and University folklore classes.
The manuscript material dates from 1945 through 1979. There are four user copies cross-filed under subject, county, collector, and informant, with a master file arranged by county of origin. The subject headings include such large divisions as Tales, Songs, Riddles, Rhymes, Proverbs, Recipes, History, Medicine, Games, Festivals, Drama, Dance, and Customs, further subdivided by the culture of origin. The most heavily collected categories are "Songs," "Narrative - Personal Experience (Historical)," and "Narrative - Local Legends (Arizona)."
Also represented are administrative files, including Committee correspondence and annual reports which detail the Committee's accomplishments over the previous year.
Taped and recorded materials which correspond to some of the materials in this collection are located in the following Southwest Folklore Center manuscript collections: L. Marguerite Collier Collection, SWF 005; Southwest Folklore Center Pre-1980 Phonodisc Collection, SWF 007; and Southwest Folklore Center Field Recording Collection, SWF 011.
Gillmor, Frances, 1903-; Granger, Byrd H; Folklore -- Arizona; Folklore -- Mexico -- Sonora (State); Folklore -- Southwest, New; Folk literature, Spanish -- Arizona; Folk songs, Spanish -- Arizona; Folk songs, Spanish -- Mexico -- Sonora (State); Corridos; Mexican Americans -- Arizona -- Music; Mormons -- Arizona -- Music; Mexicans -- Music; Folk music -- Arizona; Interviews; Clippings; Correspondence
Container List
- Series I: General Administrative Records, 1943-1977
  Summary reports, annual reports, general correspondence,
  - Folklore Committee annual reports. 1943-1976 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - General correspondence. 1967-1977 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Graduate folklore program correspondence. 1968-1977 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - NEH Grant Applications. 1971-1976 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Series II: Subject Files, 1945-1979
  Folklore materials arranged according to subject. Subjects include folk beliefs, children's lore, customs, festivals, games, Native American lore, medicine and folk narratives.
  - Subject files: Beliefs, Children's Lore, Customs, Festivals (Celebrations), Festivals (Dance), Festivals (Drama), Games, Indian Lore, Medicine, Narrative; mythical tale I (Creation, Animal Tales), Narrative; mythical tale II (Supernatural, Magic), Narrative; mythical tale III (Jokes, Anecdotes), Narrative; local legends (Europe, U.S.). 1945-1979 (Box 2)
  - Subject files: Narrative; local legends (Arizona), Narrative; personal experience (Historical), Narrative; personal experience (Supernatural), Narrative; pychological interpretation, Proverbial sayings. 1945-1979 (Box 3)
  - Subject files: Recipes, Songs, Speech. 1945-1979 (Box 4)
- Series III: Collector Files, 1945-1979
  Identical subject matter as the Subject Files series, arranged by collector rather than by subject.
  - Collector files: A - C 1945-1979 (Box 4)
  - Collector files, D - L 1945-1979 (Box 5)
  - Collector file, M - Z 1945-1979 (Box 6)
- Series IV: County Files, 1945-1979
  Identical subject matter as the Subject Files series, arranged by Arizona county rather than by subject.
  - County files, A - Pima 1945-1979 (Box 7)
  - County files, Pima (continued) - Yuma 1945-1979 (Box 8)
- Series V: Informant Files, 1945-1979
  Identical subject matter as the Subject Files series, arranged by informant rather than by subject.
  - Informant files, A - C 1945-1979 (Box 8)
  - Informant files, D - O 1945-1979 (Box 9)
  - Informant files, P - Sh 1945-1979 (Box 10)
  - Informant files, Si - Z 1945-1979 (Box 11)
- Series VI: Master Files, 1945-1979
  This series contains original documents, copies of which are filed in the previous series. Use of material in this series is by permission only. Researchers must obtain permission from the coordinator of the University of Arizona Southwest Folklore Center or the University of Arizona Manuscripts Librarian in order to use materials from this series.
  - Master files, Apache - Pima (Sells) 1945-1979 (Box 12)
  - Master files, Pima (Tucson) - Santa Cruz 1945-1979 (Box 13)
  - Santa Cruz (continued) - Yuma. 1945-1979 (Box 14)